                                                                     MACHINE LEARNING WORKSHEET – 1

In Q1 to Q7, only one option is correct, Choose the correct option:

1.   The value of correlation coefficient will always be:                      ( C )

A) between 0 and 1                                  B) greater than -1
C) between -1 and 1                                 D) between 0 and -1

2.   Which of the following cannot be used for dimensionality reduction?       ( C )

A) Lasso Regularisation                             B) PCA
C) Recursive feature elimination                    D) Ridge Regularisation

3.   Which of the following is not a kernel in Support Vector Machines?        ( B )

A) linear                                           B) Radial Basis Function
C) hyperplane                                       D) polynomial

4.   Amongst the following, which one is least suitable for a dataset having non-linear decision boundaries?    ( B )

A) Logistic Regression                              B) Naïve Bayes Classifier
C) Decision Tree Classifier                         D) Support Vector Classifier

5.   In a Linear Regression problem, ‘X’ is independent variable and ‘Y’ is dependent variable, where ‘X’ represents weight in pounds.    ( B )
     If you convert the unit of ‘X’ to kilograms, then new coefficient of ‘X’ will be?
     (1 kilogram = 2.205 pounds)

A) 2.205 × old coefficient of ‘X’                    B) same as old coefficient of ‘X’
C) old coefficient of ‘X’ ÷ 2.205                    D) Cannot be determined

6.   As we increase the number of estimators in ADABOOST Classifier, what happens to the accuracy of the model?   ( B )

A) remains same                                      B) increases
C) decreases                                         D) none of the above

7.   Which of the following is not an advantage of using random forest instead of decision trees?  ( B )
  
A) Random Forests reduce overfitting
B) Random Forests explains more variance in data then decision trees
C) Random Forests are easy to interpret
D) Random Forests provide a reliable feature importance estimate

In Q8 to Q10, more than one options are correct, Choose all the correct options:

8.   Which of the following are correct about Principal Components?                ( B,C )

A) Principal Components are calculated using supervised learning techniques
B) Principal Components are calculated using unsupervised learning techniques
C) Principal Components are linear combinations of Linear Variables.
D) All of the above

9.   Which of the following are applications of clustering?                        ( A,B,C,D )

A) Identifying developed, developing and under-developed countries on the basis of factors like GDP, poverty index, employment rate, population and living index.
B) Identifying loan defaulters in a bank on the basis of previous years’ data of loan accounts.
C) Identifying spam or ham emails  
D) Identifying different segments of disease based on BMI, blood pressure, cholesterol, blood sugar levels.

10. Which of the following is(are) hyper parameters of a decision tree?   ( A,D )

A) max_depth                                            B) max_features
C) n_estimators                                         D) min_samples_leaf

Q10 to Q15 are subjective answer type questions, Answer them briefly.

11. What are outliers? Explain the Inter Quartile Range(IQR) method for outlier detection.

OUTLIERS :  The Data point which lies outside(distinct) the overall distribution of the dataset is termed as Outlier.

Inter Quartile Range(IQR) method for outlier detection : 

--> IQR is used to measure variability by dividing a data set into quartiles.

--> The data is sorted in ascending order and split into 4 equal parts. 

--> Q1, Q2, Q3 called first, second and third quartiles are the values which separate the 4 equal parts.

    -> Q1 represents the 25th percentile of the data.
    -> Q2 represents the 50th percentile of the data.
    -> Q3 represents the 75th percentile of the data.

--> If a dataset has 2n / 2n+1 data points, then

    -> Q1 = median of the dataset.
    -> Q2 = median of n smallest data points.
    -> Q3 = median of n highest data points.

--> IQR is the range between the first and the third quartiles namely Q1 and Q3: IQR = Q3 – Q1.

--> The data points which fall below Q1 – 1.5 IQR or above Q3 + 1.5 IQR are outliers.


12. What is the primary difference between bagging and boosting algorithms?

Bagging:

   --> Parallel ensemble: each model is built independently

   --> Aim to decrease variance, not bias

   --> Suitable for high variance low bias models (complex models)

   --> An example of a tree based method is random forest, which develop fully grown trees 
       that RF modifies the grown procedure to reduce the correlation between trees.

Boosting:

   --> Sequential Ensemble: try to add new models that do well where previous models lack

   --> Aim to decrease bias, not variance

   --> Suitable for low variance high bias models

   --> An example of a tree based method is gradient boosting

13. What is adjusted R2 in logistic regression. How is it calculated?

Adjusted R2 : It measures the proportion of variation explained by only those independent variables 
              that really help in explaining the dependent variable. It penalizes you for adding 
              independent variable that do not help in predicting the dependent variable.

Adjuster R^2 is Caliculated by The Formulae,

R^2 adjusted = 1 - ((1-R^2)(N-1))/(N-P-1)

Where R^2 = Sample R-Square
      N   = Total sample size
      P   = Number of Predictors



14. What is the difference between standardisation and normalisation?

Normalization rescales the values into a range of [0,1]. This might be useful in some cases where all parameters 
need to have the same positive scale. However, the outliers from the data set are lost.

          Xchanged = (X−Xmin)/(Xmax−Xmin)

Standardization rescales data to have a mean (μ) of 0 and standard deviation (σ) of 1 (unit variance).

          Xchanged = (X−μ)/σ

15. What is cross-validation? Describe one advantage and one disadvantage of using cross-validation.

Cross-validation  : It is a technique in which we train our model using the subset of the data-set and 
                    then evaluate using the complementary subset of the data-set.

Advantage         : Cross Validation helps in finding the optimal value of hyperparameters to increase the efficiency of the algorithm.

Disadvantage      : Cross Validation drastically increases the training time. Earlier you had to train your model only on one training set,
                    but with Cross Validation you have to train your model on multiple training sets. 